ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education (ERIC/AE) Records
ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education (ERIC/AE) Records
1962-1973
ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education.
6 linear ft.
The ERIC/AE collection contains organizational material, correspondence, financial records, printed material, and reports related to ERIC/AE and its predecessor, the Library of Continuing Education. Printed material includes information sources, occasional papers and newsletters published by the Clearinghouse. Writings by Alexander N. Charters, Margaret Charters, Roger DeCrow, Stanley M. Grabowski, Charles Hoover, Huey B. Long, John A. Niemi, John Ohliger, Sara M. Steele and Coolie Verner are included.
149357
Biographical History
The ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education (ERIC/AE) at Syracuse University was an outgrowth of the Library of Continuing Education (LCE). LCE provided a storehouse for information in the area of adult education. During the term of the LCE contract the need arose for a different type of work than that done under the LCE contract. In the meantime the ERIC Clearinghouse network became available. ERIC Clearinghouse provided "research and research related documents to which access cannot be readily attained through any presently existing bibliographic tool". The working papers of LCE's final report indicate that the "Library of Continuing Education at Syracuse University will operate as an ERIC Clearinghouse for the period of the present contract." (Statement of Work, Library of Continuing Education, working papers)
"The ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education (ERIC/AE) was sponsored by the Educational Resources Information Center (ERIC) of the United States Office of Education and Syracuse University to provide information services to the adult education and training profession." (Continuing Education For Adults. No. 147, April 1970. p. 1) ERIC/AE gathered together information that would be of help "to adult education agencies in business and industry, churches, the military and other governmental and community organizations as well as schools and universities." (Ibid.) A National Advisory Board was established to determine what information needs were and to maintain contact with the field of adult education.
A primary function of ERIC/AE was the printing of various materials, including bibliographies, analytical reviews, Basic Literature Sources, Current Literature Sources and newsletters.
The Syracuse University contract for ERIC/AE was not renewed in 1972. At that time the Clearinghouse moved to Illinois. The Clearinghouse then moved to Ohio State where it is part of the ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult, Career and Vocational Education.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education (ERIC/AE) Records is divided into five series. Association contains material related to the development of ERIC/AE and its relationship to LCE (Library of Continuing Education). Material includes proposals and visitor lists and is arranged chronologically. Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by type of correspondence, includes letters, memos, individuals and organization and is arranged chronologically within each folder. Financial comprises budget information (1964-1973). Printed matter contains series, filed in numerical order by series number; literary reviews, in alphabetical order by title; and articles which appeared in journals, arranged in chronological order. Reports includes various reports on ERIC/AE arranged alphabetically by report title, for example "National Advisory Board, Quarterly Reports," and chronologically within each folder.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
In particular, see also the following:
Adult Education Association of the USA (AEA/USA) Records
Alexander N. Charters Papers
John Niemi Papers
Coolie Verner Papers
James B. Whipple Papers
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Charters, Alexander N.; Charters, Margaret A.; DeCrow, Roger.; Grabowski, Stanley M.; Hoover, Charles.; Long, Huey B.; Niemi, John A.; Ohliger, John.; Steele, Sara M.; Verner, Coolie.; ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education -- Records and correspondence.; Syracuse University -- ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education -- Records and correspondence.; Syracuse University -- Library of Continuing Education.; Adult education -- United States.; Adult education of women.; Continuing education.; Older people -- Education.; Articles.; Brochures.; Budgets.; Papers (document genres); Proposals.; Reports.; Adult education teachers.; Educators.; Teachers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education.
Inventory
- Association
  - Library of Continuing Education (LCE) proposals, undated (Box 1)
  - LCE/ERIC planning and evaluation papers, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - LCE/ERIC workplans, undated (Box 1)
  - LCE final report, 30 Jun 1967 (Box 1)
  - Library of Continuing Education/ERIC Clearinghouse proposal guidelines (Department of Health, Education and Welfare), 1968 (Box 1)
  - LCE plan for development, 1968-1971 (Box 1)
  - LCE reports, duplicate lists, manuscripts/archives, undated (Box 1)
  - LCE Statement of Work, Nov 1966-Mar 1967 (Box 1)
  - ERIC Clearinghouses, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - ERIC proposals, Apr 1967 (Box 1)
  - ERIC/AE proposals, contracts, 1967-1969; evaluation, Jun 1968 (Box 1)
  - ERIC, documentation of ERIC/AE visitors, Mar 1968-Oct 1970 (Box 1)
  - ERIC/AE proposal, RFP terminology., undated (Box 2)
  - ERIC/AE proposals, contracts, budget, 1968-1971 (Box 2)
  - ERIC/AE proposal renewal, 1960-1970 (Box 2)
  - ERIC/AE proposals/budget, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - ERIC/AE evaluation, 1968; "Model Information Services in Adult Basic Education" - grant proposal, 1970 (Box 2)
  - ERIC/AE proposal, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - ERIC/AE phase out, 1971 (Box 2)
  - ERIC/AE
    - Jul 1967-Jul 1969 (Box 2)
    - Jun 1971-Nov 1973 (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  - Mailing lists, undated (Box 2)
  - Memos, Feb 1967-Aug 1967 (Box 2)
  - Syracuse University Libraries memos, Jan 1966-Mar 1966 (Box 2)
  - U. S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare, 1967-1972 (Box 2)
  - Charles Hoover, Acting Chief of Central ERIC, May 1971-May 1972 (Box 2)
  - Dr. Coolie Verner, Oct 1971-May 1972 (Box 2)
- Financial
  - LCE, budget, 1964 (Box 3)
  - LCE, budget, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - LCE, budget, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - LCE/ERIC Clearinghouse, budget, Sep 1966-Jan 1967 (Box 3)
  - LCE, budget, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - LCE, budget., 1965-1968 (Box 3)
  - Syracuse University Research Corporation (SURC), budget and proposal, 1968 (Box 3)
  - LCE, budget, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
- Printed material
  - Series
    - ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education (ERIC/AE) publication lists, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - Current Information Sources/Adult Basic Education (CIS/ABE), undated (Box 4)
    - Basic Information Sources (BIS)
      - BIS No. 2. Adult Learning and Instruction, 1971 (Box 4)
      - BIS No. 17. Evening College Education, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Continuing Information Sources (CIS)
      - CIS No. 1. Higher Adult Education, 1967 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 4. Continuing Education in the Professions, 1967 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 5. Management Development, 1967 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 6. Television and Radio in Adult Education, 1967 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 8. Training of Adult Education Personnel, 1967 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 9. Public School Adult Education, 1968 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 11. Higher Adult Education, 1968 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 12. Adult Education in Africa, 1968 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 13. Adult Education in Asia, Australia and New Zealand, 1968 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 14. Education for Aging, 1968 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 15. Programmed Instruction in Adult Education, 1968 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 16. Community Education for Adults, 1968 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 17. Management Development, 1968 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 18. Adult Basic Education, 1968 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 19. Public School Adult Education, 1968 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 20. Cooperative Extension, 1968 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 21. Adult Learning Characteristics, 1968 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 23. Continuing Education of Women, 1969 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 23. Counseling and Personnel Services in Adult Education Counseling, 1969 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 27. Adult Basic Education, 1970 (Box 4)
      - CIS No. 28. Programmed Instruction in Business and Industry, 1970 (Box 5)
      - CIS No. 30. Parent, Home and Family Life Education. (Joint Publication with Adult Association of the U.S.A.), 1970 (Box 5)
      - CIS No. 32. Continuing Education of Women, 1970 (Box 5)
      - CIS No. 33. Training of Law Enforcement Personnel, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Occasional papers
      - Occasional Paper No. 21. "Community Service and Continuing Education: A Literature Review." (James B. Whipple), 1970 (Box 5)
      - Occasional Paper No. 30. "Toward a Gog and Magog or? A Critical Review of the Literature of Adult Group Discussion." (Franklin W. W. Osinski, Joh Ohliger, Colleen McCarthy), 1972 (Box 5)
      - Occasional Paper No. 32. "Pablo Freire: A Revolutionary Dilemma for the Adult Educator." (Stanley M. Grabowski), 1972 (Box 5)
      - Occasional Paper No. 34. "Consumer Education Programming in Continuing Education." (Margaret Charters), 1973 (Box 5)
      - Occasional Paper No. 35. "Conceptual Learning From Mollusks to Adult Education", 1973 (Box 5)
      - Occasional Paper No. 36. "Towards a Working Philosophy of Adult Education", 1970 (Box 5)
      - Occasional Paper No. 38. "Evaluating the Attainment of Objectives in Adult Education: Process, Properties, Problems, Prospects." (Sara M. Steel and Robert E. Brack), 1973 (Box 5)
    - Newsletter - "Continuing Education for Adults," Nos. 129-149/150, Oct 1968-May 1970 (Box 5)
    - Newsletter - "Continuing Education for Adults," Nos. 151-182, msg. 160, 166, 167, Mar 1973 (Box 5)
    - Newsletter - ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education, undated (Box 5)
  - Literature reviews
    - Adult Education, vol. XVII No. 4 (Summer), 1967 (Box 6)
    - "Adult Education and the Disadvantaged Adult" (Darrell Anderson and John Niemi), undated (Box 6)
    - "Adult Education Dissertation Abstracts, 1868-1969" (Stanley Grabowski), undated (Box 6)
    - "Adult Education in Germany: A Bibliography" (Armin L. Schadt), 1969 (Box 6)
    - "Contemporary Approaches to Program Evaluation: Implications for Evaluating Programs for Disadvantaged Adults" (Sara M. Steel), 1973 (Box 6)
    - "Continuing Education in the Health Related Professions: A Review of the Literature Pertinent to North America, 1960-1970" (June Nakamoto and Coolie Verner), 1973 (Box 6)
    - "Correspondence Study: A Summary of the Research of the Research and Development Research" (David E. Mathieson, National Home Study Council), 1971 (Box 6)
    - "Cost Benefit Analysis and the Adult Educator: A Literature Review" (Sara M. Steele), undated (Box 6)
    - "Cross Cultural Interaction Skills: A Digest of Recent Training Literature" (Roger DeCrow), undated (Box 6)
    - "Education for Aging: A Review of Recent Literature" (H. Lee Jacobs, W. Dean Mason, Earl Kauffman, Adult Education Association of the U.S.A.), undated (Box 6)
    - "The Education of the Mentally Retarded Adult: A Selective Review of Recent Literature" (Huey B. Long), 1973 (Box 6)
    - "A Handbook For Teachers of Non-English Speaking Adults" (Patricia Hefferman-Cabrera), undated (Box 7)
    - "Human Relations - Training and Research", undated (Box 7)
    - Library of Continuing Education at Syracuse University - Part I Adult Education Periodical Holdings; Part II Adult Education Newspaper Holdings. Adult Education Periodical Holdings, undated (Box 7)
    - "The Mass Media in Cooperative Extension: A Review of Recent Literature" (Jack C. Everly), undated (Box 7)
    - "The Mass Media in Adult Education. A Review of Recent Literature" (John Ohliger), 1968 (Box 7)
    - "The Mass Media in Adult Education in the Developing Countries" (David G. Guelette), 1971 (Box 7)
    - "Mass Media in Public Affairs Adult Education: A Review of the Literature" (Hilton M. Power), 1970 (Box 7)
    - "Methods and Techniques of Adult Education", undated (Box 7)
    - "A Model of Information System for the Adult Education Profession" (Roger DeCrow), undated (Box 7)
    - "NEEDS - of People and Their Communities - and the Adult Educator" (Ernest E. McMahon. Adult Education Association of the U.S.A.), undated (Box 7)
    - "Occupational Training for Disadvantaged Adults: An Annotated Bibliography" (Training Information Sources No. 2.), Jun 1970 (Box 7)
    - "Physical Facilities in the Research and Training of Adults" (memorandum on sparse research and development literature), undated (Box 7)
    - "The Preparation of Adult Educators: A Selected Review of the Literature" (Coolie Verner, Gary Dickinson, Walter Leirman, Helen Niskala; Adult Education Association of the U.S.A.), undated (Box 7)
    - Product reports, Jul 1970-Nov 1971 (Box 7)
    - Product reports, Feb 1971-Sep 1973 (Box 7)
    - "A Register of Research and Investigation in Adult Education" (Roger DeCrow and Stanley Grabowski eds.), 1968 (Box 8)
    - "Research and Investigation in Adult Education: 1969 Annual Register" (Roger DeCrow and Stanley Grabowski, eds.) (Box 8)
    - "Research and Investigation in Adult Education: 1970 Annual Register" (Roger DeCrow and Stanley Grabowski, eds.; ERIC/AE and Adult Education Association of the U.S.A.) (Box 8)
    - "Research and Investigation in Adult Education: 1971 Annual Register" (Roger DeCrow and Stanley Grabowski, eds.) (Box 8)
    - "Research and Investigation in Adult Education: 1972 Annual Register" (Roger DeCrow and Stanley Grabowski, eds.) (Box 8)
    - "Television: A Viable Channel for Educating Different Poverty Groups?--A Literature Review" (John A. Niemi and Darrell V. Anderson), 1971 (Box 8)
    - "The Use of Mass Media in Religiously Motivated Adult Education: A Review of the Literature" (Robert W. Clyde and Eugene C. Jaberg), 1970 (Box 8)
  - Articles
    - Sep 1967-Dec 1967 (Box 9)
    - Jun 1968-Dec 1968 (Box 9)
    - Jan 1969-Dec 1969 (Box 9)
    - Jan 1970-Jul 1970 (Box 9)
    - Jan 1971-Dec 1971 (Box 9)
    - Mar 1972-Nov 1972 (Box 9)
    - Jan 1973-Aug 1973 (Box 9)
    - "Higher Education in the United States: The Current Picture, Trends and Issues" (Malcolm S. Knowles, American Council on Education), undated (Box 9)
    - Adult Education Research Conference (formerly NSAER), Minneapolis, 27 Feb-2 Mar 1970, digest of papers presented to the Adult Education Research Conference (Box 10)
    - International Seminar in Continuing Education (Alexander N. Charters, ed. Publication in Continuing Education), Jun 1972 (Box 10)
    - National Seminar on Adult Education (NSAER), Chicago, 11-13 Feb 1968 (Box 10)
    - National Seminar on Adult Education Research (NSAER), Toronto, 9-11 Feb 1969; abstracts of papers (Box 10)
- Reports
  - Final report, "Adult Education Information Services: Establishment of a Prototype System. Part I", 1 Dec 1967 (Box 10)
  - Final report, "Adult Education Information Services: Establishment of a Prototype System. Part II", 1 Dec 1967 (Box 10)
  - Final report, "Adult Education Information Services: Establishment of a Prototype System. Part III", 1 Dec 1967 (Box 10)
  - Program review presentation, 1 Dec 1967 (Box 10)
  - National Advisory Board
    - 13 Nov 1967 (Box 11)
    - 4 Jan 1968 (Box 11)
    - 15 Mar 1968 (Box 11)
    - 4-6 Jun 1968 (Box 11)
    - 3-4 Dec 1968 (Box 11)
    - Minutes, 13 Nov 1967-3 Dec 1968 (Box 11)
    - 17-18 Apr 1969 (Box 11)
    - 17-18 Apr 1969, photographs (Box 11)
    - 23 Oct 1969, photographs (Box 11)
    - 3-4 Jun 1970 (Box 11)
    - 18 Jun 1971 (Box 11)
    - 4 Feb 1972 (Box 11)
    - Biographies, photographs, (1969) (Box 11)
    - Minutes, correspondence, biographies, undated (Box 11)
  - Quarterly reports
    - Oct 1967-Jan 1968, Jul 1968-Dec 1968 (Box 12)
    - Jan 1968, Jan 1970 (Box 12)
    - 6 Apr 1970 (Box 12)
    - Oct 1971-Apr 1972 (Box 12)
    - Jul 1972-Jan 1973 (Box 12)
    - Mar 1973-Sep 1973 (Box 12)
  - Review of ERIC/AE (Knox Committee), 1971 (Box 12)
  - Syracuse University Libraries' Report to Syracuse University: The Library Building Program, Oct 1965 (Box 12)
  - University College, Annual Reports "Continuing Education at Syracuse University" University Annual Report, 1954-1963 (Box 12)
  - United States Department of Education, progress reports, procedures, undated (Box 12)